Guide to the Leland Stanford Collection SC0512
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leland Stanford collection
1869-1975
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University
SC0512
4.5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
The collection contains primary and secondary sources pertaining to the life of Leland Stanford and the history of Stanford University's founding. Includes clippings, correspondence, articles, pamphlets, speeches, scripts, reports, memorabilia, and copies or facsimiles of historical documents.
Biographical / Historical
Leland Stanford was born March 9, 1824 in Waltervliet Township, New York. He was admitted to the practice of law in 1848 and married Jane Lathrop in 1850. In 1852 Stanford moved to California where he first worked as a storekeeper in Mother Lode mining camps and later became a successful Sacramento businessman. Stanford was a leader in organizing the Republican party in California and was elected governor in 1861 at the age of 37. Early in the 1860s Stanford joined with three other Sacramento merchants--Charles Crocker, Mark Hopkins, and Collis P. Huntington--in the building of the Central Pacific Railroad. In 1884, Leland and Jane founded Leland Stanford Jr. University in memory of their son. Stanford died June 21, 1893 during his second term as United States Senator.
Related Materials
For materials created by Leland Stanford, see Stanford University Archives collection number SC0033A (Leland Stanford Papers).
Acquisition Information
The materials in this collection were separated from the old Leland Stanford Papers (now collection number SC0033A) when the collection was reprocessed in 1996.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Description of the Collection
This collection contains primary and secondary sources pertaining to the life of Leland Stanford and the history of Stanford University's founding. Included are clippings, correspondence, articles, pamphlets, speeches, scripts, reports, memorabilia, and copies or facsimiles of historical documents. In addition to the business and political career of Leland Stanford, subjects include his ideas on education, the naming of Palo Alto, Stanford family genealogy, railroad history (especially the completion of the transcontinental railroad), Thomas Hill and his painting "Driving the Last Spike," Eadweard Muybridge and the invention of motion pictures, Stanford's residences in Sacramento and San Francisco, Vina Ranch, and Warm Springs Ranch.
Gold Spike.; Leland Stanford House (Sacramento, Calif.); Palo Alto (Calif.); Warm Springs Ranch (Calif.).; Vina Ranch (Calif.); Clark, George A. (George Archibald); Lampson, Robin; Kimball, Sarah Louise; Hill, Thomas A.; Jordan, David Starr; Scibird, Ruth.; Myrick, David F.; Central Pacific Railroad Company; Stanford, Leland; Stebbins, Horatio; Browne, Louise M.; Stanford, Arthur W.; Stanford, Grant Lansing.; Hemsing, Peter.; Stanford University; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Fisher, Helen Dwight.; Wooster, C. M.; Farnham, Wallace D.; Curtis, Edward.
- Biographical and Historical Materials, Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of clippings, pamphlets, articles, copies or facsimiles of historical documents, speeches, scripts, and correspondence of researchers and University officials. Subjects include Stanford's political career, his years in Port Washington, Wisconsin, his ideas on education, the University's history, and the naming of Palo Alto. Also included are eulogies and memorial addresses following Stanford's death.
  - Clippings (photocopied), 1873-1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (photocopied), 1885-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings (photocopied), 1893-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (photocopied), 1894-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings (photocopied) - miscellaneous and undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Periodicals, 1858-1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Weekly Times (San Francisco), 1859 Jul 16
    - Tribune Almanac and Political Register for 1862
    - Harper's Weekly, 1864 Jan 23
  - Periodicals, 1874, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    California Mail Bag, August 1874 (2 copies), with 1916 clipping of photograph of six men still living who were present at the driving of the last spike in 1869.
  - Periodicals, 1885-1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Coast Review, 1887 Aug
    - "Millionaires of the Pacific Coast," The Cosmopolitan, 1887 Aug
  - Periodicals, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Santa Clara (see p. 21), 1893 Feb
    - Report, San Jose, 1893 Jun 7
    - Jordan, "The Educational Ideas of Leland Stanford," Sequoia, 1893 Sep 13
    - The Seaport News, 1893 Jun 24
    - Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper (reception of Stanford at Sacramento on return from European tour), 1890 Nov 8
    - Smith, Augustine J., "A Picture and a Reflection," from National View, 1893 Jul 15
  - Periodicals, 1894-1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Periodicals, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Periodicals, 1933-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes California Freemason, Winter 1964, with article on Stanford as an Freemason
  - Census returns, photocopies, 1860-1880 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Second ward, Sacramento, census return, 1860
    - Fourth ward, Sacramento, census return, 1870
    - San Francisco census return, 1880
  - Scrapbook of clippings on Stanford and Republican politics, 1857-1863 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Schooling, Clinton, New York, 1844-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Rudd, Helen N., "A Century of Schools in Clinton" - pamphlet
    - Letter, W. H. Cowley to E. B. Graves, 1966 Jul 28
    - Clinton Liberal Institute, catalogue (verifax copy), 1844
    - Maps of Clinton - copies, 1858, 1874
  - Port Washington - Washington's Birthday Ball, 1850, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Facsimile of original invitation, 1850
    - Clippings re ball, 1922
    - Letters accompanying clippings, 1922
  - Port Washington - Masonic Order, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Note on Stanford's Masonic membership, undated
    - Whicher, John, "Masonic Beginnings in California and Hawaii" (pamphlet)
    - Bridgman, Louis W. "Leland Stanford of Port Washington," Wisconsin Freemason, 1955 Nov
    - Two items on Leland Stanford Lodge in Chico, CA
  - Pacific Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1868-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Facsimile copies of Stanford's policy, 1868
    - Correspondence concerning location of the original, 1968
    - Press release and correspondence concerning board room of Stanford University trustees in Pacific Mutual Building, 1962
    - Nunis, Doyce B., Past is Prologue; A Centennial Profile of Pacific Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1968
  - Stanford University: role of spiritualism in its conception, 1901-1906 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jordan to H. C. Nash, recounting Stanford's denial of role of sprititualism in founding University (carbon), 1901 Jul 27
    - Clippings from The Pantagraph, Bloomington, IL, concerning spiritualist founding of University, 1906
    - G. A. Clark to editor of The Pantagraph, refuting story, 1906 Jul 9
  - Stanford University: Stanford's ideas on education, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Memorandum on talks on education between Senator Stanford and President Jordan, 1893 Nov
    - Clipping: Stanford's last letter to Jordan laying out his ideas on the future of the University
  - Stanford University: naming of Palo Alto, 1888-1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Memorandum of Stanford's itinerary, 1888-1892
    - C. M. Wooster to Prof. Emory Smith, re securing name of "Palo Alto" to replace "University Park", 1929 Jun 12
  - Sonnet on the Return of Senator Stanford, by P.M.K., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Death of Leland Stanford: poetry and memorials, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Death of Leland Stanford: eulogy by Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, Leland Stanford Division No. 283, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Death of Leland Stanford: Memorial Addresses on the Life and Character of Leland Stanford, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Addresses delivered in Senate and House of Representatives; includes biographical sketch and account of his funeral - 2 copies, different bindings
  - Death of Leland Stanford: Memorial Addresses, 1892-1893 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Memorial Addresses Delivered in the Senate (2 copies), 1892
    - Remarks by Hon. John H. Mitchell (2 copies), 1893
    - Address of Hon. J. N. Dolph, 1892
  - Death of Leland Stanford: letter re pallbearers, 1949 Nov 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    G. W. Burbank to C. M. Buckley, listing locomotive engineers who were Stanford's pallbearers
  - Albany Hall of Fame, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Stanford elected in 1946
  - Biographical articles, 1894-2008 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Carriages, clippings on restoration of Stanford carriages, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Curtis, Edward, "Leland Stanford, a Biography" (3 copies), 1880 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Pamphlet also includes biography of William Watt and an essay on viticulture (3 copies)
  - Fisher, Helen Dwight: correspondence and articles, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Ruth Scibird and Guy Miller on her research for "The Stanford Family Album" and her memo on errors, 1947-1950
    - Typescript biography of Leland Stanford (carbon copy)
  - Founders Day, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Remarks by Carl Loeffler
    - Remarks by Senator Charles B. Henderson
    - Article by Cedric Larson, directed to Stanford Illustrated Review
  - Hemsing, Peter, "The Stanfords in Europe", 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Student paper from Humanities 102
  - Radio and TV scripts, 1950-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Press release for "Taste of a Millionaire," KPIX show on the Stanford house in San Francisco, 1962
    - "Gold Rush Days," radio script (episode on Leland Stanford) with letter by Walter C. Peterson, 1950
  - Shaw, Albert, "Leland Stanford: Some Notes on the Career of a Successful Man.", 1893 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    from the Review of Reviews, Vol. 8, No. 43
  - Stebbins, Horatio - speeches on Stanford, 1893-1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Remarks at Stanford's funeral (pamphlet), 1893
    - Manuscript speech on Stanford, undated; with accompanying letter by Archibald Treat, 1939
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman - letters received re sources, 1925-1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Crook to Wilbur re disposal of papers of Thomas W. Stanford, 1925 Mar 25
    - Hopkins to Wilbur re traveling with the Stanfords, 1925 Apr 21
    - Gage to Wilbur with transcript of clipping on railroad history and Stephen Gage, 1934 Jan 18
  - Albany Rural Cemetery, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 11.1)
    - Stanford Family, Friends of Albany Rural Cemetery, Vol. 8 Issue 1, 2003
    - Two pages on the restoration of the Stanford Family Mausoleum in the Albany Rural Cemetery, 2001
  - The Resources of California, September 1886 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Includes long articles on founding of LSJU and the life of Leland Stanford; two originals and photocopy
  - Sacramento Bee, "The Centennial Album", 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - San Francisco News Letter and California Advertiser, Vol. 32, No. 23 (see page 11), 1881 Dec 17 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Reports of Cases Determined in the Supreme Court of the State of California, Vol. 126., 1900 (Box 9)
    See page 112 for case involving the estate of Leland Stanford, 1899
- Central Pacific Railroad, Series 2
  This series consists of pamphlets and memorabilia on the railroad and the "Gov. Stanford" locomotive.
  - Central Pacific Railroad: pamphlet from 50th anniversary of inauguration of construction at Sacramento in 1863, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Central Pacific Railroad: items on locomotive "Gov. Stanford" and miscellaneous materials, 1930-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Southern Pacific Bulletin, article on the "Gov. Stanford" locomotive, 1963 Jul
    - Words and music to "Utah Iron Horse"
    - D. L. Joslyn to Frank B. Lemor (Stanford Museum) re the locomotive "Gov. Stanford", 1930 Aug 12
    - Clippings on "Gov. Stanford" and the history of CPRR, 1950-1960
  - Central Pacific Railroad: Southern Pacific Pensioners reunion programs, 1912-1916 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 3rd Annual Reunion and Luncheon, 1912
    - 7th Annual Reunion and Luncheon [addresses by D.S. Jordan and R.L. Wilbur], 1916
- Genealogy, Series 3
  This series includes correspondence and notes of several genealogists, a few photocopied family documents, and correspondence with Stanford descendants.
  - Browne, Louise M.: Correspondence, essays and notes, 1918-1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Stanford descendants, 1948-1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Kimball, Sarah L.: correspondence, notes, 1922-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Maternal line: Phillips genealogy, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scibird, Ruth, genealogical notes and one Lathrop document, circa 1830, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes list of birth and death dates for Dyer Lathrop and his siblings, ca. 1830
  - Stanford, Arthur W., Stanford Genealogy: Comprising the Descendants of Abner Stanford, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Stanford, Arthur W., genealogy, 2 microfilm reel(s) (Box 3A)
  - Stanford, Grant Lansing, genealogy, 1 microfilm reel(s) (Box 3A)
  - Stanford, Grant Lansing, Stanford Genealogy, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical notes and essays, author unknown, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Genealogical notes and essays, author unknown; photostats of 1775 and 1780 documents, 1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Genealogical miscellaney: clippings and publication, 1888-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - A Christmas Reminder; Being the Names of About Eight Thousand Persons.. .Confined on Board the British Prison Ships During the War of the Revolution. Brooklyn, NY, 1888
    - Clippings, 1907, 1959-1967
- Gold Spike, Series 4
  This series contains programs, clippings, and talks from the Gold Spike Centennial events, 1969; other pamphlets, clippings, articles, and correspondence on the history of the Gold Spike; and a pamphlet, clippings, and correspondence pertaining to Thomas Hill's painting "Driving the Last Spike."
  - Driving the Gold Spike, 1869-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "The Last Spike Driven. The Dream of Benton and Whitney Fulfilled," The Railroad Record (typescript copy), 1869 May 13
    - Program from Golden Anniversary held in San Francisco, 1919
    - Letter by Frank Calvin, researcher for Cecil B. DeMille, re Stanford missing the spike, 1939 Aug 21
    - Union Pacific ad featuring photo from the movie "Union Pacific" (Stanford hitting the spike), 1944
    - Southern Pacific ad featuring photo of Stanford's train making its way to Promontory Point
    - Corliss, Carlton J., text of talk on American railroad collections and memorabilia, 1956
    - "American Railroads," pamphlet with mention of Gold Spike
    - Golden Spike Ceremony booklets, 1957, 1963
    - Postcard of "last spike" monument in Utah
  - Stanford University press releases, 1954-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Receipt for the Gold Spike, 1869-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Copies of receipt for engraving done on Gold Spike, 1869
    - Lampson, Robin, "The Man Who Gave the Golden Spike," California Monthly, 1940 Mar
    - Lampson, Robin, "Story of the Golden Spike," newspaper story, and two letters re use of image of the receipt, 1968
    - The Bulletin (Southern Pacific) with photo of six men who witnessed driving of the last spike, 1916 Jun
    - Clipping on finding of the receipt, 1937
  - Driving of the Gold Spike: clippings (general), 1950-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Golden Spike Centennial: programs and ephemera, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Programs, brochures, memos, calendars, and other items pertaining to centennial events in Utah, May 1969
  - Golden Spike Centennial: texts of talks, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Farnham, Wallace D., "Leaders, Law and the Golden Spike: or, the Treaty of Hooper's House"
    - Farnham, Wallace D., "Contending Galaxies: Railroad Leaders and the Race to Promontory"
    - Myrick, David F., "Refinancing and Rebuilding the Central Pacific: 1899-1910"
    - Fehrenbacker, Don, remarks as commentator on above papers
  - Golden Spike Centennial: special section from the Sacramento Bee, 1969 May 4 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Golden Spike Centennial: clippings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Golden Spike Centennial: clippings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Golden Spike Centennial: clippings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Golden Spike Centennial song "Wedding of the Rails", 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Sheet music
    - Letter to Ralph Hansen from composer, Lorraine S. Wilkinson, with brochure and clipping
  - Golden Spike Centennial: magazines, pamphlets and other publications, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Book Club of California, three keepsakes
    - Golden West Books, brochure on railroad history books
    - Montana Post (Montana Historical Society)
    - Scholastic Newstime
    - American Geograpical Society, ad for the book The Golden Spike
    - Brochure by Brigham City Chamber of Commerce
    - Article by R. Hansen in Stanford Library Bulletin
    - Lawyers Title News
  - Golden Spike Centennial: magazines, pamphlets and other publications, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Brochure on the Wells Fargo Bank Historical Collection
    - Wilson, R. L., The Golden Spike; pamphlet published by Colt Industries
    - Carter, Kate, ed., First Transcontinental Railroad in Picture and Story, Daughters of Utah Pioneers
    - Utley, Robert, Golden Spike, National Park Service booklet
    - National Park Service brochure on the Golden Spike National Historic Site
  - Golden Spike Centennial: magazines, pamphlets and other publications, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Railway Age, issue on 100 years after the Golden Spike, 1969 May 10
    - Railway Journal, cover illustration of driving the Golden Spike, 1959 May
  - Lampson, Robin, articles on the "missing spike" with replies by Ralph W. Hansen, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The "missing silver spike": press release and clipping, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Clippings on the Gold Spike (not centennial), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Southern Pacific's The Gold Spike Album: brochure and color slides of the artwork in the album, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Hill's painting "Driving the Last Spike", 1881-1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Hill, Thomas. The Last Spike; San Francisco, 1881
    - Clippings about Hill and the painting, 1909-1915
    - Typescript copies of correspondence between Hill and H. C. Peterson, 1905-1906
    - Typescript copy of a clipping on the painting, 1939
    - Letter to Jeanette Hitchcock from Elliot Evans, re W. S. Jewett's possible role in the Gold Spike painting, 1949
  - "A Railroad and a Golden Spike" by Margo Lundell, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Eadweard Muybridge, Series 5
  This series pertains to Muybridge's photographic experiments at Stanford's Palo Alto Farm and a subsequent law suit and includes photocopies of correspondence and depositions and exhibits gathered for the trial; transcript of court record; and other articles and clippings.
  - Muybridge vs. Stanford: photocopies of depositions and exhibits gathered for the trial., 1883 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Muybridge vs. Stanford: photocopies of depositions and exhibits gathered for the trial., 1883 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Muybridge vs. Stanford: photocopy of defendant's exhibit, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Muybridge vs. Stanford: photocopies of correspondence and deposition of Frank Shay, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Muybridge vs. Osgood, publishers: transcript of original court record done in 1928, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Articles and clippings on Muybridge's photographic work, 1922-1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Ott, John, "Iron Horses: Leland Stanford, Eadweard Muybridge, and the Industrialized Eye," Oxford Art Journal, Vol. 28, No. 3, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Palo Alto Farm, Series 6
  This series consists of articles, clippings, press releases, and brochures about the winery on the Farm.
  - Palo Alto Farm Winery: articles, clippings, press releases, and brochures, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Residences, Series 7
  This series includes clippings, articles, booklets, and reports on the Stanfords' residences in Albany, Port Washington, Michigan Bluffs, Sacramento, and San Francisco. The San Francisco materials include floor plans and description by Bertha Berner, Jane Stanford's secretary.
  - Residence - Albany, NY: clipping and typed description, 1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Residence - Port Washington, Wisc: clippings, article, photograph, correspondence, and copied documents, 1849-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Photocopies of legal documents signed by L. Stanford, 1849-1850, and letter from Charles L. Larson, 1979, accompanying these copies
    - Clippings about Stanford in Port Washington, 1947-1965, and photo of building that housed his law office, 1964
    - Photocopies of 1895 clipping on the Stanfords in Wisconsin
  - Residence - Port Washington, Wisc: articles, 1947-1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Residence - Michigan Bluffs, Calif: clippings, 1903-1954 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Residence - Sacramento, Calif: clippings, letters, and miscellany, 1862-1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Includes 1862 newspaper illustration of the house on silk
  - Residence - Sacramento, Calif: booklets, 1958-1968 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Old Sacramento, a Report on Its Significance..., Part I and Part II, 1958
    - Old Sacramento Inventory of Historical Buildings, 1962
    - Neasham, V. Aubrey, Old Sacramento a Reference Point in Time, Sacramento Historic Landmarks Commission, 1968
  - Residence - Sacramento, Calif: interpretative plans prepared for the Stanford Mansion State Historic Park, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Applegate, Brenda J. The Stanford's Sacramento House: A Typical Eclectic Victorian, 1992
    - Taugher, Sandy. Furnishing Plan for the Stanford Mansion Master Bedroom during the late 1860s, 1993
    - Taugher, Sandy, Furnishing Plan for the Dressing Rooms of the Master Suite, 1993
  - Residence - Sacramento, Calif: renovation campaign and reopening as California's Center for Protocol, 1998-2005 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Fundraising brochures
    - Brochure of the Leland Stanford Mansion Foundation
    - invitation and program from Opening Gala, 2005
    - Clippings
  - Residence - San Francisco, 1943-1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Berner, Bertha: notecards from 1943 talk, holograph description and floor plan of house, and typed description.
    - Clipping re TV program on the house, 1962
    - Nagel, Gunther, "Monument to Elegance: Leland Stanford's Nob Hill Mansion," The American West, 1975 Sep
- Other Properties, Series 8
  This series contains clippings, brochures, correspondence, scripts, and ephemera on Vina Ranch and Warm Springs Ranch
  - Vina Ranch - clippings, brochures, correspondence, and TV script, 1891-1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Clippings re Vina Ranch and the Clairvaux Abbey established there in 1955, 1891-1965
    - Certificates for cattle brands, 1920-1938; and correspondence re cattle brands, 1947-1964
    - TV script, "The Vina Story," Chico State, 1958
    - Book Club keepsake on Vina, 1955
    - Brochure on the New Clairvoux Abbey, circa 1960
  - Warm Springs Ranch - clippings, ephemera, and miscellany, 1870-1962 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1900-1962
    - Menu from Hidden Valley Ranch, circa 1950
    - Letter by R. E. Kelly to Emory E. Smith re history of Warm Springs with attached excerpts from the Centennial Yearbook of Alameda County, 1932
    - A Legend of Warm Springs, by H. W. (Sacramento: Russell & Winterburn), 1870
- Miscellaneous Materials, Series 9
  This series includes memorabilia from railroad organizations using Stanford's name, correspondence and clippings pertaining to questionable historical claims, proposed commemmorative stamps from the 50th anniversary of the University, and a copy of The Monarch Philanthropist, a "fable" based on the life of Stanford.